A Finding Aid to the Reginald R. Isaacs Papers, circa 1842-1991, bulk 1928-1991, in the Archives of American Art AAA.isaaregi
Archives of American Art
Reginald R. Isaacs papers
bulk 1928-1991
circa 1842-1991
AAA.isaaregi
Archives of American Art
22.4 Linear feet
The papers of Reginald R. Isaacs measure 22.4 linear feet and date from 1842 to 1991, with the bulk of the material from 1928 to 1991. The collection includes Isaacs's personal and professional papers, as well as extensive research material he collected and created for his two-volume biography, Walter Gropius: The Man and His Work.
Reginald R. Isaacs
Biographical Note
Born in Canada in 1911, Reginald R. Isaacs began working in architectural offices at age 14, later coming under the influence of "Beaux-Arts diplomes" at the University of Minnesota and Harvard and subsequently under that of Walter Gropius at Harvard University. He later studied sociology and planning at the University of Chicago under Louis Wirth and Rexford Guy Tugwell.
Isaacs served on the staffs of city planning commissions in Minneapolis, Syracuse, and Chicago, and in the federal government in the National Youth Agency, Public Housing Authority, and Housing and Home Finance Agency. His architectural practice in Minneapolis, Washington, D.C., Chicago, and other cities included the design of housing, colleges, and hospitals. He was director of planning and development for Michael Reese Hospital in Chicago, 1945-1953, where Walter Gropius, planner Walter Blucher, and sociologist Louis Wirth collaborated with him as consultants. He was a United Nations expert on regional planning in South America, and a planning consultant for the Ford Foundation, the U.S. State Department, Puerto Rico, and the Virgin Islands.
Recommended by Walter Gropius, Isaacs served as the Charles Dyer Norton Professor of Regional Planning at Harvard University from 1953-1978. He was also Chairman of the Graduate School of Design's Departments of City and Regional Planning as well as Landscape Architecture. Throughout his career he lectured at universities throughout the United States and in almost every country of Central and South America and in the Caribbean.
In 1962 Isaacs and Gropius began their collaboration on Walter Gropius: The Man and his Work, until the death of Gropius in 1969. The first volume of the biography was published in German in 1983, with the second volume following in 1984. Isaacs died of a massive heart attack in 1986, never realizing his goal to see an English-language edition which was published posthumously in 1991 by the Estate of Reginald Isaacs.
1911 Born in Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada
1935 Received Bachelor of Architecture degree from the University of Minnesota
1939 Received Masters of Architecture degree from Harvard University, Graduate School of Design
1947-1950 Studied sociology and planning with Louis Wirth and Rexford Guy Tugwell at the University of Chicago
1945-1953 Director of planning at Michael Reese Hospital, Chicago, Illinois
1951-1953 Guest lecturer at Harvard University's Graduate School of Design with Walter Gropius and also served a two-year term as a member of the Board of Overseers Committee to Visit the Graduate School of Design
1953-1978 Named the Charles Dyer Norton Professor of Regional Planning
1953-1964 Chairman of the Department of City and Regional Planning
1953-1958 Chairman of the Department of Landscape Architecture
1962 Began collaboration with Walter Gropius on the biography Walter Gropius - The Man and his Work
1969 Walter Gropius dies
1983 Walter Gropius, Der Mensch und Sein Werk, Volume 1 published by Gebr. Mann Nerlag, Berlin
1984 Walter Gropius, Der Mensch und Sein Werk, Volume 2, published by Gebr. Mann Nerlag, Berlin
1986 Isaacs dies
1991 Walter Gropius: An Illustrated Biography of the Creator of the Bauhaus, published by the Estate of Reginald Isaacs. The Papers of Reginald R. Isaacs donated to the Archives of American Art by his son, Henry Isaacs.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of of architect, instructor, writer, and city planner, Reginald R. Isaacs (1911-1986) measure 22.4 linear feet and date from 1842 to 1991 with the bulk of the material dating from 1883 to 1985. The collection includes Isaacs's personal and professional papers, as well as extensive research material he collected and created for his two volume two-volume biography of Bauhaus architect, Walter Gropius: Walter Gropius: The Man and His Work. The bulk of Walter Gropius' papers are housed at the Busch Reisinger Museum at Harvard University, and the Bauhaus Archiv in Germany.
Series 1 to 12 contain contain biographical, legal, and financial material; personal and professional correspondence; project and subject files; writings and publications; teaching files; works of art; scrapbooks; printed material; and photographs relating to Isaacs' personal and professional career.
Series 13 forms the bulk of the collection and pertains specifically to the writing and publication of Isaacs' biography of Gropius. It contains research material, correspondence (much of it with Gropius), drafts of the manuscript, publication correspondence, photographs and illustrations, and printed material. Some of the research material, including some of the photographs and illustrations that were used in the biography, appear to have been original documents of Walter Gropius, while large portions of the material are photocopies of the originals, many of them in German.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into fourteen series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1935-1986, undated (Boxes 1, 22; 8 folders)
Series 2: Legal Material, 1976-1984, undated (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Financial Material, 1945-1969 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Correspondence, circa 1891, 1936-1986 (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Project Files, 1948-1980, undated (Box 2, OV 23; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Subject Files, 1961-circa 1982, undated (Box 3; 2 folders)
Series 7: Writings, 1940-1986, undated (Boxes 3-4, 22; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 8: Teaching Files, 1954-1973 (Boxes 4-5; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 9: Works of Art, 1965-1967, undated (Box 5, OV 23; 3 folders)
Series 10: Scrapbooks, 1929-1969 (Box 5; 2 folders)
Series 11: Printed Material, 1842-1844, 1913-1986, undated (Box 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 12: Photographs, 1959-1981, undated (Boxes 5, 22; 7 folders)
Series 13: Walter Gropius Biography, circa 1880s-1991, undated (Boxes 6-22, OV 23, MGP 1, MGP 2, MGP 4; 16.0 linear feet)
Series 14: Unprocessed Addition, 1974-1985 (Box 24; 1.0 linear foot)
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Henry Isaacs, son of Reginald Isaacs, in January 1991. An additional 1.0 linear foot was donated by Merry White, daughter of Reginald Isaacs, in 1997.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is restricted to the Washington, D.C. research facility. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Bauhaus.; Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969; Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956; Architects; Architects and community; Architects and housing developers; Architects in government; Architectural writing; Architecture and society; Architecture, Modern; Architecture, Modern--20th century; Authors; City planners; City planning; Educators--Massachusetts; Exhibition catalogs; Industrial designers; International style (Architecture); Photographs; Schools of architecture; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Writings
- Biographical Material, 1935-1986, undated; Series 1; 8 Folders Boxes 1, 22
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains biographical material about Isaacs such as biographical sketches, educational records, and obituaries. The award found here is a citation from the Society of American Registered Architects from 1942. Isaacs's wedding announcement, an employee identification card from Chicago, Illinois, and an enlistment card for "C" Company of the 3rd Regiment of the New York Guard can be found in the folder housing miscellaneous material.
  - Biographical Sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1950-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diplomas and Transcript (photocopies), 1935, 1939, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Architecture Licenses (photocopies), 1940, 1941, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates of Membership and Award, 1941, 1942, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Oversized 1972 award in Box 22, Folder 1.
  - Obituaries and Eulogy, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Society of American Registered Architects Award, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Legal Material, 1976-1984; Series 2; 3 Folders Box 1
  This series contains the last will and testament for Reginald and Charlotte Isaacs and includes related correspondence and drafts of the documents.
  - Wills, Correspondence, and Drafts, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wills, Correspondence, and Drafts, Reginald R. Isaacs, 1982, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wills, Correspondence and Drafts, Charlotte Alders Isaacs, 1982, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Material, 1945-1969; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1
  This series contains cancelled checks for art related purchases and donations by Reginald and Charlotte Isaacs. Signatures that can be found here include those of Herbert Bayer, William Hunt, Fernand Leger, Jackson Pollock, Reba Stewart, and Jack Shadbolt.
  - Cancelled Checks, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, circa 1891, 1936-1986; Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence of Reginald R. Isaacs, with copies of his replies.
  Arrangement note
  The series is organized into two subseries.
  4.1: Chronological Correspondence, 1936-1986, undated
  4.2: Alphabetical Correspondence, circa 1891, 1941-1985
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1936-1986, undated; 4.1
    Correspondents from 1936 to 1940 include Frank Lloyd Wright and the Chicago Planning Commission. Records from these years also include performance appraisals from the Federal Security Agency's National Youth Administration.
    1941 to 1945 correspondents include Marcel Breuer on the purchase of a Fernand Leger painting; Walter Blucher on the Michael Reese Hospital project; Hubert H. Humphrey; Mies van der Rohe; the Federal Works Agency's United States Housing Authority; and the National Housing Agency regarding notification of personnel action.
    1946 to 1950 correspondence concerns the Michael Reese Hospital project; Rexford G. Tugwell; the University of Chicago regarding enrolling for a Doctor of Philosophy in Sociology; and activities as a panel speaker for the Citizens' Housing and Planning Council of Detroit.
    Correspondents from 1951 to 1955 include Hubert H. Humphrey, Leon Eugene Arnal, Jose Luis Sert, Rafael Pico, Earl H. Reed, Chester Nagel, Edward Everett Horton's (autograph), Christian Herter, Leverett Saltonstall, Nathan M. Pusey (President of Harvard University on Urban Renewal project), Peter Nash, Walter H. Blucher, and Lewis Mumford. The records also contain correspondence with Adlai Stevenson on nominating Ferd Kramer for an award; and letters of congratulations on appointment as the Charles Dyer Norton Professor of Regional Planning and Chairman of the Regional Planning and Landscape Architecture Department of Harvard University.
    Correspondents from 1956 to 1960 include William F. Buckley, Jr., on Dr. von Mises', Jose Luis Sert, Lewis Mumford, Edwin S. Burdell, President of The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, Lewis Mumford, Jasper D. Ward (Architect of General Electric Company) on the project "Research for Living," Rexford G. Tugwell, Leverett Saltonstall, Hubert H. Humphrey, John F. Kennedy, Paul Douglas on Senator John Sparkman's bill S. 1230, Candido Oliveras (Chairman of the Puerto Rico Planning Board on the Southern Metropolitan Area Project), Fernando Belaunde Terry, and Richard M. Bennett.
    1961 to 1965 correspondents include John A. Holabird on an urban design project, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., Fernando Belaunde Terry, and Francois C. Vigier.
    1966 to 1970 correspondents include Lewis Mumford, Walter F. Bogner, and Abraham A. Ribicoff.
    Correspondents from 1966 to 1970 include Everett McKinley Dirksen, Ralph M. Paiewonsky (Governor of the Virgin Islands), Hubert H. Humphrey, Jorge Ricardo Riba (Director of Instituto de Vivienda y Urbanismo in Panama), and Luis A. Ferre (Governor of Puerto Rico).
    Correspondents from 1971 to 1975 include Fernando Belaunde Terry, and Frank O. Gehry which includes the publication Children and the City, by Olga Adams.
    1976-1980 correspondents include William Saltzman, Newton S. Friedman, Arete Publishing Company, Inc. on manuscripts for an encyclopedia, and The Free Press on biographies for the Macmillan Encyclopedia of Architects.
    1981-1985 correspondents include Jeffrey Potter on Jackson Pollock, Kazuhiko Satani of the Satani Gallery in Tokyo, Ati (Beate) Gropius Johansen, Norma Farber, Fernando Belaunde Terry, William W. Nash, Jr., Newton S. Friedman, Leone Blooston, Bruno Zevi, Robert Rosenthal, Chester Nagel, Howard Henry, Harry Seidler, and Ferd Kramer.
    1986 correspondence includes sympathy cards to Charlotte Aldes Isaacs.
    - Correspondence, General, 1936-Sept. 10, 1986, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13-62)
  - Alphabetical Correspondence, circa 1891, 1941-1985; 4.2
    Subjects covered by the correspondence found in this subseries include the publication of various works by Isaacs, Isaacs' work as a consultant, various exhibitions, conferences, and lectures, and sales of Isaacs' artwork. There are also files relating to Isaacs' collection of paintings by Jackson Pollock and Emil Singer which document Isaacs' dontaion of Pollock paintings to the Fogg Museum at Harvard University, and his sale of Singer etchings in the United States. In addition to correspondence, files may contain writings, teaching material, and printed matter.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by name or subject.
    - Architectural History Foundation, Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 63-65)
    - Walter Blucher, 1960, 1982-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 66-69)
    - Cambridge Boat Club, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Columbus Town Meeting, Columbus, Ohio, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Committee for Economic Development, Washington, D.C., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - John M. Gaus, 1941-1970 (Box 1, Folder 73-81)
    - Goethe Institute Boston, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts, 1964-1985 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Walter Gropius (and Ise), 1945-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-34)
      Regarding the Michael Reese Hospital project, Gropius as Architectural Consultant, 1945-1953, and collaboration on the biography.
    - About Charles Wilson Killam, 1961-1962, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Jack (Jacobus Josephus) Liebenberg, 1979, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36-39)
    - The M.I.T. Press, 1969, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Mount Auburn Hospital, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - About Richard Nelson, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Rafael Pico, 1959, 1961, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
    - Jackson Pollock's Artwork, 1956, 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 45-55)
    - Royal Society for the Encouragement of Arts Manufactures and Commerce, 1977-1985 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Emil Singer, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 58-59)
    - University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Francois C.D. Vigier, 1970, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 61-64)
      Writings by Vigier.
- Project Files, 1948-1980, undated; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2, OV 23
  These files concern Isaacs' involvement in various projects, including his work as a planning and landscape consultant with Hideo Saski and Chester Nagel at Springfield College, and elsewhere. Correspondence and other records relating to reports written by Isaacs can also be found here.
  This series is arranged chronologically by date of project.
  - Leon Arnal, Retirement and Scholarship Funds, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Includes photographs of Arnal.
  - Springfield College, Massachusetts, 1954-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 66-71)
  - Housing Association of Metropolitan Boston, Massachusetts, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Jewish General Hospital, Montreal, Quebec, Canada, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - McLean Hospital, Belmont Massachusetts, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Guatemala City, Guatemala, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    Includes correspondence with Harland Gibson and Gustavo W. Jacobsthal.
  - Reconnaissance in Latin America, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 76-77)
  - Don Mills Development, Limited, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 1959-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Butler Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island, 1962-64 (Box 2, Folder 79-80)
  - British Virgin Islands, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 81-82)
  - Ford Foundation Urban and Regional Redevelopment Advisory Program in Chile, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Deaconess Hospital, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 84-85)
    Oversized plats in OV 23.
  - "A Program of Urban and Regional Planning Studies at the University of Alabama...," Alabama, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Instituto Medico del Norte, Puerto Rico, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Hospital Dr. Pila, Puerto Rico, 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Oversized Plat, Deaconess Hospital, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, circa 1966 (Box OV 23)
- Subject Files, 1961-circa 1982, undated; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 3
  This small series contains writings and photographs concerning Katherine McNamara's retirement, and clippings and printed material concerning Horatio Alger.
  - Katherine McNamara's Retirement, 1961, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Horatio Alger, 1962-69, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Writings, 1940-1986, undated; Series 7; 2 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 22
  This series includes writings by Isaacs other than the biography of Walter Gropius, which is documented in Series 13.
  The series is organized into three subseries.
  7.1: Lectures and Articles, circa 1940-1986
  7.2: Biographical Entries, undated
  7.3: Publications, 1944-1974
  - Lectures and Articles, circa 1940-1986; 7.1
    This subseries contains many of Isaacs's lectures and articles in draft or photocopy form.
    Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - "Air Raid Shelters for Private Residences and Housing Projects," with Henry G. Hunt, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Preliminary," for a Radio Address Given by Homer Hoyt, c. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "City Planning", circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Summary of Text of Preliminary Master Plan of Recreation Areas," Chicago Plan Commission, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Outline for "Areas for New Growth, Profitable Plans for New Areas, Trends in Subdivision Planning, Effects of Subdivision Planning on Real Estate, Decentralization - An Evil?," with Victor H. Bringe, 1945 October (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Community Organization for Planning and Action", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "The Neighborhood Concept in Theory and Application," Journal of Land Economics, 1949 February (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Public Relations for Architects," Public Relations Committee Preliminary Report on Policy and Program, American Institute of Architects, Chicago Chapter, 1949 November (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "The Rape of the Lake", 1947-1972 (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
      Oversized photograph in Box 22, Folder 2.
    - "A Tribute to Louis Wirth," South Side Planning Board, Annual Meeting, Chicago, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Administrative Aspects of Rehabilitation," Discussion, New England Conference on Neighborhood Improvement, 1954 February (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Inter-professional Relations," Report, A.I.A. 86th Annual Convention, 1954 June (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Planners in History", 1954 December (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Careers in Planning," Harvard University Career Conference, 1955 March (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Providing for Future Urban Growth," Ohio State University Conference on Slum Prevention and Neighborhood Rehabilitation, 1955 March (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Training for the Planning Profession," University of San Juan, 1956 April (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Core of the City: A Pilot Study of Changing Land Uses in Central Business Districts, by John Rannells, Reviewed by Isaacs, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Obligations of Good Practice," The Standards of Professional Practice, A.I.A. Document 330, 1957 March (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Geography and Natural Resources Administration in the United States," by Meredith F. Burrill, Reviewed by Isaacs, 1957 July (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Observations on Being a Slave in the Market - A Report from an Ex-job Seeker," American Society of Planning Officials, comments by Isaacs, 1957 July (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Flyspeck, U.S.A. - Portrait of a Village", 1957 December (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Urban Sprawl - Patterns, Implications and Prospects," National Health Forum, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - "Who Killed the Fallen Sparrow?," Urban Sprawl and Health, National Health Council, 1959 January (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "A Preliminary Survey of Objectives, Policies, Program and Organization," Area Planning Association, Boston, Massachusetts, 1959 February (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Social Planning in the Community," Cambridge Community Center, 1959 May (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Citizen Education, Organization, and Participation - A Program for Puerto Rico," American Society of Planning Officials, 1959 May (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Estetica Del Area Metropolitana," Associacion Argentina De Planeamiento, 1959 October (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "The Real Costs of Urban Renewal", c. 1960 (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
    - "History: Its Effects on Tomorrow's Architecture," Architecture Plus for 1960, A & M College of Texas, 1960 February (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Puerto Rico and the 'Junta,'" Draft, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Educacion en Planificacion", 1960 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "The Role of Educational Plant Planners in Urban Renewal," Overview Magazine, with William Nash, 1961 April (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "Consideration of the Culture of Puerto Rico in Planning and Architecture", 1961 June (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "The Education of Planners and Architects", c. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "Planning the South Shore's Future, the South Shore Region, 1837-1937, the Present 1987-2087, a Retrospective and Prospective Study," with Francios Vigier, 1962 January (Box 3, Folder 42-43)
    - "Statements for WGBH-TV," regarding planning in Metropolitan Boston, 1962 January - (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Goals for Planning," an audit of University of Buffalo, New York, 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Metas Ideales Para Planeamiento", 1962 February (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "The Design of Low-rent Public Housing - A Statement for the Housing Yearbook", 1962 April (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Goals for 2012: A Retrospective and Prospective View of the Twin Cities", 1962 April - (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
    - "The Education of Planners - An Epilogue", 1962 April - August (Box 3, Folder 50-54)
    - "Minneapolis Community Improvement Program - Proposed Work Program - Urban Design Studies", 1962 August - November (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Fuera de Brasil Y Mexico...", c. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Walter Gropius and the Form of Cities", 1963 April (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Art in Latin American Architecture, by Paul F. Damaz, reviewed by Isaacs, 1963 August (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "El Programa de Renovacion Comunal", 1964 April (Box 3, Folder 59)